<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<main>
	<cast>
		<penelopeCruz>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">PENÉLOPE CRUZ – </span>After having appeared in "Live Flesh", "All About my Mother" and "Volver", Penélope has worked again with Pedro Almodóvar.<br/><br/>After studying acting at Cristina Rota's school, she made her debut while still a teenager in "Jamón, Jamón" (1992). In this film she already showed an extraordinary capacity for playing the common characters which would bring her such success in the future, and also attracted the attention of the most important Spanish directors with whom she would later work. Bigas Luna in the above mentioned "Jamón, Jamón" and "Volaverunt", Fernando Trueba in "Belle Epoque" and "La niña de tus ojos" (for which she received the Goya for Best Actress), Alejandro Amenábar in "Abre los ojos" or Agustín Díaz Yanes in "Sin noticias de Dios". She has also had a more than notable international career which includes "The Hi-Lo Country" (Stephen Frears), "All the Pretty Horses" (Billy Bob Thornton), "Blow" (Ted Demme), "Captain Corelli's Mandolin" (John Madden), "Vanilla Sky" (Cameron Crowe), "Non ti muovere" (Sergio Castellito), "The Good Night" (Jake Paltrow), "Vicky Cristina Barcelona" (Woody Allen) or "Nine" (Rob Marshall).<br/><br/>With "Non ti muovere", by Sergio Castellito, she won the David di Donatello award and the European Film Academy's People's Choice Award for Best Actress. The New York Times selected her, for that film, as one of the ten best female performances of the year. With "Volver" she won the Best Actress award at the Cannes Festival, ex aequo with the other actresses in the film. She also won the EFA and the Goya and was nominated for the Academy Award, the Golden Globe and the BAFTA awards.<br/><br/>Her performance in "Vicky Cristina Barcelona" has earned her more than ten awards and an Academy Award for Best Supporting Actress.<br/><br/>She doesn't discount the possibility of directing in the future and in the meantime she is experimenting with photography, one of her favourite pastimes.]]>
		</penelopeCruz>
		<lluisHomar>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">LLUIS HOMAR – </span>Born in Barcelona 51 years ago, Luis has managed to combine theatre with cinema and television, although he has devoted most of his extensive career to the stage. He studied Law at Barcelona's Autonomous University after which he attended various acting courses: Uta Hagen (1986-87) in New York or John Strasberg (1985) among others.<br/><br/>He was one of the founders of the Teatre Lliure and was its director from 1992 to 1998. He has acted in and directed over thirty productions for the company. In 1999, he directed and starred in Shakespeare's "Hamlet" for the Festival Grec. Among the authors he has staged and performed are David Mamet ("Speed the Plow") Molière ("George Dandin", "Le misanthrope" and "L'école des femmes") and Ibsen ("Hedda Gabler" and "The Master-Builder"), Pirandello ("Mountain Giants") and Thomas Bernhard ("Histrionics").<br/><br/>He has appeared in over thirty films, working with directors such as Pilar Miró ("El pájaro de la felicidad"), Vicente Aranda ("Si te dicen que caí"), Mario Camus ("Después del sueño", "Adosados" and "La ciudad de los prodigios"), Julio Medem ("Caótica Ana"), Montxo Armendáriz ("Obaba") and Jose Luis Iborra ("El sueño de Valentín") among others.<br/><br/>In "La mala educación" he played one of the key characters, Mr. Berenguer, and had a great success. This is why he has now worked again with Almodóvar in "Los abrazos rotos". In 1986 he won the National Acting Award, in 2000 the Silver Fotogramas for Theater and the Butaca Award for Best Catalonian Actor for "Valentín".]]>
		</lluisHomar>
		<blancaPortillo>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">BLANCA PORTILLO – </span>Born in Madrid in 1963, she studied at the Higher Royal School of Dramatic Art where she began a successful theatre career. This has earned her such recognition as the La Celestina and Max awards for "Madre, el drama padre", the Max, Union of Actors and Teatro de Rojas awards for "Como en los mejores familias" or the Miguel Mihura and Union of Actors awards for "La hija del ire", by the prestigious director Jore Lavelli.<br/><br/>She has appeared in some thirty theatre productions. At present she is starring in "Hamlet", directed by Tomaz Pandur, with whom she also worked in "Barroco". José Carlos Plaza directed her in "After Play" by Brian Friel, which was a huge success, and Andrés Lima directed her in "Hamelin", by Juan Mayorga.<br/><br/>Very popular thanks to the TV series "Siete Vidas", Blanca has also worked in fifteen films, with directors such as Milos Forman ("Goya's Ghost"), Agustín Diaz Yanes ("Alatriste"), Belén Macías ("My Prison Yard") and Gracia Querejeta ("Siete mesas de billar francés"). In 2005, she began her collaboration with Pedro Almodóvar in "Volver".<br/><br/>She was nominated for a Goya as Best Newcomer for "El color de las nubes" (Mario Camus) and as Best Supporting Actress for "Volver". She won the Union of Actors award in that category for the film.<br/><br/>At the Cannes Festival, she received the Best Actress award ex aequo with the rest of the actresses for "Volver" and the Silver Conch for Best Actress at the San Sebastian Festival or "Siete mesas de billar francés".]]>
		</blancaPortillo>
		<joseLuisGomez>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">JOSÉ LUIS GÓMEZ – </span>He trained as an actor in the Institute of Dramatic Art in Westphalia (Bochum) and at the Jacques Lecoq School (Paris). He did his early professional work as actor and director in the main theatres of the Federal Republic of Germany. In 1971 he came back to Spain where he produced, directed and performed in productions such as "Report for an Academy", by Kafka, "Gaspar", by Peter Handke and "The Resistible Rise of Arturo Ui", by Bertolt Brecht.<br/><br/>After his leading role in the film "Pascual Duarte", by Ricardo Franco, for which he won the Best Actor award at the Cannes Film Festival (1976), he worked with directors such as Jaime de Armiñán ("Nunca es tarde"), Juan Sebastián Bollaín ("Las dos orillas"), Enrqiue Brassó ("In memoriam"), Jaime Camino ("Luces y sombras"), Jaime Chavarri ("Dedicatoria"), Manuel Gutiérrez Aragón ("Sonámbulos"), Eloy de la Iglesia ("La estanquera de Vallecas"), Joseph Losey ("Les routes du sud"), Pilar Miró ("Beltenebros"), Carlos Saura ("Los ojos vendados" and "El séptimo día"), Gonzalo Suárez ("Rowing with he Wind"), Mariano Barroso ("Hormigas en la boca") and Milos Forman ("Goya's Ghosts") among others.<br/><br/>In 1978, after a period of studies in New York with Lee Strasberg, he took over the management of the Centro Dramático Nacional, along with Nuria Espert and Ramón Tamayo, and two years later that of the Teatro Español.<br/><br/>In 1992, he directed "La vida es sueño" in the Théâtre de l'Odéon and the following year "Carmen" in the Opéra de la Bastille, both in Paris.<br/><br/>Since then, he has concentrated on the conception, administration and management of the Teatro de la Abadía, opened in 1995, where he has tackled a wide repertory, encouraged the training of actors and invited important European directors.<br/><br/>In 2008, he directed the opera "Simon Boccanegra", by Verdi, in the Gran Teatre del Liceu. He has won numerous awards, the most notable of which include, as well as the above mentioned Best Actor award at the Cannes Film Festival, the National Theater award, Chevalier de l'Ordre des Arts et des Letters, granted by France, the Knight's Cross of the Order of Merit of the Federal Republic of Germany, the Gold Medal from the Círculo de Bellas Artes and the Gold Medal for Merit in Fine Arts from the Spanish Ministry of Culture.]]>
		</joseLuisGomez>
		<rubenOchendiano>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">RUBÉN OCHENDIANO – </span>Born in 1980, he studied acting with Juan Carlos Coraza, contemporary dance with Michelle Mann, Eileen Standley and Mónica Page, and singing with Inés Rivadedeira, as well as other courses which enriched his theatrical training. He has worked in highly successful TV series such as "El comisario", "Hospital Central", "Al salir de clase" and "Periodistas".<br/><br/>In theatre, he has worked for such directors as Antonio Mercero in "The Green Fields of Eden" and Miguel Narros in "Así es… si así os parece", for which he was nominated as Best Leading Actor by the Union of Actors.<br/><br/>He has made over fifteen films, including "Silencio roto", by Montxo Armendáriz, for which he was nominated for a Goya for Best Newcomer, "Guerreros", by Daniel Calporsoro, "La flaqueza del bolchevique", by Manuel Martín Cuenca, for which he was again nominated by the Union de Actores, "Chill Out!", by Félix Sabroso and Dunia Ayaso, "Tapas", by Juan Cruz and José Corbacho, for which he won the "El Mundo" award, "Che", by Steven Soderbergh,"My Prison Yard", by Belén Macías and "Biutiful", by Alejando González Iñárritu.]]>
		</rubenOchendiano>
		<tamarNovas>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">TAMAR NOVAS – </span>At only 22, he can boast of having worked with some of the most important directors in Spain, Alejandro Almenábar, José Luis Cuerda or Gerardo Herrero, as well as this film by Pedro Almodóvar.<br/><br/>He began studying dramatic art with Juan Carlos Coraza. His first film was "La lengua de las mariposas", by José Luis Cuerda (1999) which was followed by "The Sea Inside", by Alejandro Amenábar, for which he received the Goya for Best Newcomer and the Union of Actors award in the same category. In 2006, he worked in "Goya's Ghosts" with the director Milos Forman and the following year in "Una mujer invisible" by Gerardo Herrero. He has worked in TV series such as "Cuenta atrás", "La señora" and "Siete vidas", among others.<br/><br/>He made his debut in theater with the play "La noche" by Bernard Mari Koltés, directed by Carlos Neira.<br/><br/>He is undoubtedly one of the rising stars of Spanish cinema.]]>
		</tamarNovas>
	</cast>
</main>