<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<main>
	<filmmakers>
		<pedroAlmodovar>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">PEDRO ALMODÓVAR – </span>He was born in Calzada de Calatrava, province of Ciudad Real, in the heart of La Mancha, in the 50s. When he was eight, he emigrated with his family to Estremadura. There he studied for his elementary and high school diplomas respectively with the Salesian Fathers and the Franciscans.<br/><br/>At seventeen, he left home and moved to Madrid, with no money and no job, but with a very specific project in mind: to study cinema and direct films. It was impossible to enrol in the Official Film School because Franco had just closed it. Despite the dictatorship that was suffocating the country, for an adolescent from the provinces Madrid represented culture, independence and freedom. He worked at many, sporadic jobs but couldn’t buy his first Super-8mm camera until he got a “serious” job at the National Telephone Company of Spain in 1971. He worked there for twelve years as an administrative assistant, he shared this job in the mornings with other multiple activities which provided his real training as a filmmaker and as a person. In the mornings, in the Telephone Company, he got an in-depth knowledge of the Spanish middle class at the start of the consumer era, the seventies, its dramas and its misfortunes, a real gold mine for a future story teller. In the evenings and nights, he wrote, loved, acted with the mythical independent theatre group Los Goliardos and made films in Super-8 (his only school as a filmmaker). He collaborated with various underground magazines and wrote stories, some of which were published. He was a member of a parodic punk-rock group, Almodóvar and McNamara, etc. And he had the good fortune that his personal explosion coincided with the explosion of the democratic Madrid of the last seventies, early eighties. That was the period the world knew as La Movida.<br/><br/>His films are the heirs and the witnesses of the brand new born Spanish democracy. After a year and a half of eventful shooting on 16mm, in 1980 he opened “Pepi, Luci, Bom”, a no-budget film made as a cooperative effort with the rest of the crew and the cast, all beginners, except for Carmen Maura.<br/><br/>In 1986, he founded the production company El Deseo S.A. with his brother Agustín. Their first project was “Law of Desire”. Since then, they have produced all the films that Pedro has written and directed, and have also produced other young directors.<br/><br/>In 1988, “Women on the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown” brought him international recognition. Since then, his films have opened all around the world. With “All About my Mother” he won his first Academy Award for Best Foreign Film, and also the Golden Globe, the César, 3 European Film Awards, the David de Donatello, 2 BAFTAs, 7 Goyas and 45 other awards. Three years later, “Talk to Her” had the same or better fortune (Academy Award for Best Script, 5 European Film Awards, 2 BAFTAs, the Nastro de Argento, the César and many other awards throughout the world but not in Spain).<br/><br/>He produced four very special films, highly rated throughout the world for their valour and delicacy (“My Life Without Me”, “The Holy Girl”, “The Secret Life of Words” and “The Headless Woman”, by Isabel Coixet and Lucrecia Martel alternatively). In 2004, “Bad Education” was chosen to open the Cannes Festival. It received extraordinary reviews throughout the world. It was nominated for numerous awards (Independent Spirit Awards, BAFTAs, César, European Film Awards) and won the prestigious Award for Best Foreign Film given by the New York Critics’ Circle and also the Nastro de Argento.<br/><br/>In 2006 he is awarded with the Prince of Asturias Award to the Arts. That very same year he presents “Volver” in competition in the Cannes Film Festival, where it got the Best Screenplay Award as well as the Best Actress Award for the six actresses of the film, leaded by Penélope Cruz. The film received 5 EFA awards, 5 Goya awards, the Fipresci award, the National Board of Review, and many others (up to 72). Penélope was nominated to the Best Actress Academy Award, being the first time a Spanish actress was nominated for a Spanish speaking film. Up to now, “Volver” has been his most popular film in terms of box office.]]>
		</pedroAlmodovar>
		<agustinAlmodovar>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">AGUSTÍN ALMODÓVAR – </span>Born in La Mancha, he graduated in Chemical Sciences from Madrid’s Complutense University.<br/><br/>Since 1985 he has worked actively in cinema. He joined the crew of “Sé infiel y no mires con quien” (Fernando Trueba) as production trainee. That same year he began his ceaseless participation in his brother’s films, working as assistant director on “Matador” and in 1986 he and Pedro set up their own company, El Deseo.<br/><br/>Since then he has produced all of Pedro’s feature films (winning the Academy Award for Best Foreign Film with “All About my Mother”) and has also produced the work of other directors (Alex de la Iglesia, Mónica Laguna, Daniel Calparsoro, Guillermo del Toro, Isabel Coixet, Félix Sabroso and Dunia Ayaso, Lucrecia Martel and Belén Macías). With El Deseo, he has also been involved in numerous coproductions with France.<br/><br/><br/>]]>
		</agustinAlmodovar>
		<estherGarcia>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">ESTHER GARCÍA – </span>Esther, who was born in Segovia, has won five Goyas for “Acción Mutante”, “All About my other”, “The Secret Life of Words” and “Volver”. She has been production director on over ninety films and TV series since she began in 1976 with “Curro Jiménez”.<br/><br/>She has worked in every aspect of production from trainee to executive producer, a position she has held since the film “My life without me” (Isabel Coixet). As well as working uninterruptedly with Pedro since “Matador”, she has done production work for Fernando Trueba, Mariano Ozores, Luis María Delgado, Gonzalo Suárez, Emilio Martínez Lázaro and Fernando Colomo.<br/><br/>As part of the El Deseo team, she has directed production on “Acción Mutante” (Alex de la Iglesia), “Tengo una casa” (Mónica Laguna), “Pasajes” (Daniel Calparsoro), “The Devil’s Backbone” (Guillermo del Toro), “Chill Out!” (Félix Sabroso and Dunia Ayaso) and “My Prison Yard” (Belen Macías).<br/><br/>Along with Agustín Almodóvar, she has gone into television production (“Mujeres”, by Dunia Ayaso and Félix Sabroso) and international production (“My life without me” and “The Secret Life of Words”, by Isabel Coixet, “The Holy Girl” and “The Headless Woman”, by Lucrecia Martel).]]>
		</estherGarcia>
		<albertoIglesias>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">ALBERTO IGLESIAS – </span>Born in San Sebastian in 1955, he studied piano, guitar, counterpoint and harmony with Blanca Burgaleta and Francisco Escudero in his home city. He broadened his studies in Paris with Francis Schwartz and in Barcelona with Gabriel BrnÇic. He has collaborated with Carlos Saura, Bigas Luna, Julio Medem and Iciar Bollaín, among others.<br/><br/>He has developed a close collaboration with Pedro since they first worked together on “The Flower of my Secret”, and since then he has been the regular composer on his films.<br/><br/>His soundtracks include “Los amantes del círculo polar” (Julio Medem), “All About my Mother”, “Talk to Her” and “Volver” (Pedro Almodóvar). He has received seven Goyas for his work on the above mentioned films and also for his scores for Julio Medem’s films “La ardilla roja”, “Tierra” and “Sex and Lucia”. He won the European Film Award (EFA) for “Volver”.<br/><br/>He was nominated for the Oscar for “The Constant Gardener” (Fernando Meirelles) and “The Kite Runner” (Marc Foster). He won the National Cinema Award in 2007. His most recent works include “Che” (Steven Soderbergh).<br/><br/>In addition to his film work, he has composed symphonic and chamber music and also several ballets for the National Dance Company.]]>
		</albertoIglesias>
		<joseSalcedo>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">JOSÉ SALCEDO – </span>The master of editors, Pepe Salcedo has edited over ninety films to date, including Pedro Almodóvar’s entire filmography.<br/><br/>He was assistant to Pedro del Rey and Pablo del Amo and began his career with the film “Una mujer prohibida”. Since then he has won three Goyas for his work on “Womenon the Verge of a Nervous Breakdown” (Pedro Almodovar), “Nadie hablará de nosostros cuando hayamos muerto” (Agustín Díaz Yanes) and “All About my Mother” (Pedro Almodóvar). He has worked along with some of the most important Spanish directors, including Manuel Gutiérrez Aragón, Eloy de la Iglesia, Pedro Olea, Gonzalo Suárez, Jaime Chávarri, José Luis Borau, Manuel Gómez Pereira and many, many more.]]>
		</joseSalcedo>
		<redrigoPrieto>
			<![CDATA[<span class="headline">RODRIGO PRIETO – </span>He was born in Mexico in 1965 and has already worked on more than twenty films as director of photography. A specialist in creating atmosphere and in the mastery of chiaroscuro, he is known for his unconventional use of the camera. He has worked with directors such as Curtis Hanson (”8 Mile”), Spike Lee (“The 25th Hour”), Oliver Stone (“Alexander”), Kevin MacDonald (“State of Play”) and, as well as being director of photography on all of Alejandro González Iñárritu’s films, he has collaborated on Ang Lee’s last two films “Brokeback Mountain”, for which he was nominated for the Oscar for Best Photography, and “Lust, Caution”.]]>
		</redrigoPrieto>
	</filmmakers>
</main>